Sumo stance is not [__] better for
your glutes in any capacity. But sumo
deadlifts aren't a great exercise to
build your glute. Here is why sumo is
not the best for your [__] glutes.
>> The wider the stance does not mean more
glutes. That's a big misconception. If
your glutes aren't growing, squat
normally don't do sumo squats. Are these
biomechanical bros telling the truth, or
is there more to the story? In this
video, we're going to review all the
evidence pertaining to sumo/wide
versus conventional/narrow.
Welcome to the channel. My name is Brett
Conturus. I'm also known as the glute
guy. I've been lifting weights for 34
years and I've been a personal trainer
for 30 years. I've owned gyms for the
past 20 years. I invented the barbell
hip dust in 2006 and I invented the
entire glute niche. I love all things
glutes. I love biomechanics. I love
every aspect of strength training from
bodybuilding to strength sports even to
physical therapy. It involves helping
you look and feel better. Then that's my
passion. For those of you who are new to
the channel, I offer Booty by Brett for
programming and I have BC Strength where
we sell highquality glute equipment
especially designed for women and for
home gym. You might want to look at BC
Strength for your lady because when she
gets better glute development, who
benefits more, you or her? Nevertheless,
welcome to the channel. So, this is an
interesting topic for me because I was
born in 1976, right? I'm 49 years old. I
started lifting in 1992 when I was 16
years old. And from 1992 to I would say
2020. So for about 28 years, sumo/wide
stance was thought to be better for
glute development than
conventional/narrow stance. And then in
2020, the tides turned. This is when Tik
Tok was on the rise. We had some
influential content creators point out
that wide stance is probably more
adductor and therefore perhaps it's less
glute. And the biomechanical bros ran
with it. For a solid year or two, all I
saw was sumo is all adductor, zero
glutes. And I made a post back in 2021,
I believe, saying sumo isn't no glutes.
It could be just as much glutes. But I
didn't elaborate like I will today. That
post seemed to have calmed things down,
but it didn't squash things. And I still
to this day see people claiming that
sumo is very ineffective for glute
development and that you should always
go narrow no matter what the instance.
Now, I wish we could point to a handful
of studies on the topic and say, "Look,
there are five hypertrophy studies that
have been conducted. In fact, we have a
review paper and a meta analysis,
including these five papers, but we
don't have any of that." As of November
2020, there are zero training studies
examining wide versus narrow stances on
glute hypertrophy. Crazy. You'd think
someone along the way would have been
interested in this topic. In the absence
of training studies actually measuring
hypertrophy, we have to go down the list
and look at biomechanical clues. So, in
today's video, we're going to look at
four different lines of evidence, all of
which are problematic. We're going to
look at anecdotes and discuss the
pitfalls of that. We're going to look at
EMG and hip loading research and discuss
their shortfalls. We're going to look at
muscle length and discuss the
limitations of that. And we're going to
look at mechanical tension and discuss
the problems with that line of research.
But this is what being evidence-based is
all about. So, first up, anecdote. All
right, you the listener are watching
this and you probably feel very strongly
about sumo versus conventional or wide
versus narrow just like I do. But your
opinion on the topic is likely very
influenced by your hip anatomy. Let's
talk about myself for a minute. I love
sumo and flaring my feet out. It feels
so much better for me. If I do low bar
sumo box squats or even free squats
where I do them very glute dominantly,
you know, sitting really far back and
feeling that stretch load on the glutes,
I actually have to worry about tearing
my glutes. Like that's how much tension
is put on the glutes. So for me, I think
they're one of my best glute exercises.
I mean, it's literally the only exercise
I have to worry about. So for me, it
could be numera uno. And yes, I feel
more stretch loading on the glutes doing
wide sumo than I do doing narrow work,
but that's probably influenced by my hip
anatomy. I've always walked duckfooted.
I even take a wide stance when I walk.
People see me walking and they make fun
of me. And I've been that way my whole
life. A lot of my family members walk
that way. I've trained clients over the
years who can't tolerate sumo. It hurts
their hip. So you, the listener, are
probably going, "Yeah, that's me. I hate
sumo. It doesn't feel right for me." Or
you might say, "I hate going narrow.
That doesn't feel right for me. For me,
going super narrow hurts my hips and I
feel like I can't get that deep. So, for
that reason alone, we cannot go by
anecdotes because it's so influenced by
our hip anatomy. But also, a huge
confounder is that no lifter ever just
does wide or narrow. We all do a blend.
Case in point, most lifters do single
leg work. So yes, you might do your
squats and your deadlifts and maybe even
your leg press all in a sumo stance, but
when you do single leg work like
step-ups, Bulgarians, lunges, or even
single leg RDL's or even single leg hip
thrust, you are using a narrow stance.
You never go out wide with those. You
can't you would fall over. Now yes, you
could do like ballerina Bulgarians to be
more abducted and make it more
replicable to sumo, but hopefully you
get my point. Even single leg leg press,
we tend to put our foot in the middle.
So, whenever someone sees good glute
gains, you never really know what
exercise it came from. Unless, for
example, you've been on a particular
routine and then you switch the focus.
Like, let's say you've always done
narrow and then you switch to sumo and
you notice a ton of glute growth. Yes,
then that's very telling. But it's
rarely the case where we just change up
one thing. In our normal training, we
change too many things and we fail to
control the variables, rendering
anecdotes unreliable for solid evidence.
Now, let's talk about EMG and hip
loading studies. I currently have a
folder with 29 of these studies, okay?
Looking at either EMG activity with the
glutes going narrow versus wide or like
hip loading. We call them moments, which
is kind of like the torque requirements
on the hips during a movement. So, while
I'm talking, I'll show you the 29
studies, but I'm not going to review
them for three reasons. Number one, we
found out in the 2023 Plotkins study
that EMG does not predict hypertrophy.
It probably predicts active muscle
force. well but not stretch and both are
important for muscle growth active and
passive muscle force. So EMG alone
doesn't tell the whole story. Also hip
moments don't predict hypertrophy
because you can have greater hip
extension requirements or greater hip
abduction or external rotation moments
and requirements. But there are multiple
hip extensors, multiple hip abductors
and multiple hip external rotators. So
if an exercise involves more hip
extension moments that could be carried
out by the glutius maximus or it could
be carried out more so by the adductor
magnus or the hamstrings. Same with for
example say seated hip abduction which
is transverse plane abduction. Well that
could be the glutius maximus or it could
be the posterior fibers of the glute
medius and minimus or the deep hip
external rotators like the purformis. So
while EMG and hip moments give you clues
they don't provide solid evidence. So,
I'm not going to look into much. And I
also want to mention that these papers
are very conflicting. Like, you can find
a variety of papers showing that sumo is
superior for glute EMG activity and
loading on the hips and several papers
showing it's inferior. So, if someone
wanted to cherrypick, they could make a
compelling case either way. Now, let's
talk about anatomy. There are a couple
of recent papers that provide good clues
about this topic of sumo versus
conventional. The first is Anoti 2025.
And this paper showed that we've been
wrong the entire time about where we
thought that the glutes attached to.
Looks like we got the origins right, but
the insertions wrong. Crazy to find that
out in 2025. But you can see in this
image here that the upper and lower
glutius maximus are distinctly separate
structures. They originate and insert
into different places. And you can see
that the lower fibers are much longer
than the upper fibers. Next up is
another brand new study, Takahashi 2025.
And this paper is really cool because
check out this image. You see the hip
center of rotation. Okay, I want you
guys to look at this image and picture
doing abduction. Picture raising your
leg out to the side. Well, the fibers
above the center of rotation would
shorten. So when you go wide, those
fibers would get shorter, but the fibers
below the center of rotation would
elongate. So the lower glutius maximus,
you can see would get longer from sumo.
And that's just in the frontal plane.
But then they took it a step further and
they looked at specific torqus produced
by the different fibers. And what they
found was the superior glutes create a
net abduction moment. Meaning that when
activated, they will tend to pull the
leg outwards. But the lower glutius
maximus, the inferior fibers have the
opposite effect. They will tend to pull
the leg inwards and have an adduction
moment because they're stretched when
you go wider. When activated, it's going
to pull in a little bit. So the net
effect of the entire glutius maximus
contracting would be a neutral effect
because the abduction torqus generated
by the upper fibers and the adduction
moments generated by the lower fibers
cancel each other out. Pretty
fascinating paper, but that does give us
clues that maybe sumo is better for the
lower glutes. And then finally, this
same PlotKin 2023 paper I talked about
that showed that EMG did not predict
hypertrophy. This study did find that
the lower glutius maximus grew the most
in comparison to the upper and middle
fibers. So, I'll put the image up here.
As you can see, the squat group, upper
glute max grew 12.8%, middle 10.1% and
lower 19.2%. And with the hip thrust
group, upper glute max 13.7%, middle
10.7%, and lower 21.5%. So, you're
almost seeing double the growth in the
lower glutius maximus because the glute
max is just thicker in the lower region.
And this is important because Tik Tok
and Instagram have made the shelf
popular over the last several years.
Everyone's talking about upper glute
growth. In fact, this was talked about
in bikini as well. Bikini competitions,
all the feedback was always you need
more upper glutes. But before 2020, from
like far back as I remember, like in the
'9s up until like 2020, the upside down
heart-shaped glutes sought after. And
it's that lower glute max development
that everyone wanted. The problem with
that is a lot of the exercise best for
the lower glutes also work the legs very
well making it tough to just build lower
glute max. Your vertical hip extension
exercise all your squats, single leg
squatting movements like step-ups,
lunges and Bulgarians and your
Romanians, single leg Romanians, good
mornings, even leg press, single leg leg
press, they tend to activate the lower
glute max a little better than they do
the upper glute max. But I should
mention that the Plotkins study found
similar growth between squats and hip
thrusts in all three regions. Casting
doubt on whether you can truly isolate
lower versus upper glute max growth. We
need more research on that too.
Nevertheless, these just provide us with
clues and should be taken into
consideration. But now let's talk about
muscle length. Let's talk about stretch.
So I'm bringing out skelly here and it's
difficult to model this because there is
a lot of interindividual variability
with attachment points. Now the glute
max originates on the pelvis, the
sacrum, even the coxix and it inserts
onto the glutial tuberosity. But like I
said, there's a lot of variation here.
So as I mentioned, because the leg kind
of comes inwards, let's see how you have
some of the upper fibers contracting. As
this would pull together, you could see
how it would shorten and kind of raise
the leg outwards. However, if you have a
lower fiber, you can see here how going
wider would lengthen the glute a little
bit. So the lower glute max fibers would
be lengthened a little bit from going
wider. And while I love using the
skeleton for demonstration purposes and
I think it's invaluable for
biomechanist, a couple problems with the
skeleton is is this to scale? Did they
get the hip anatomy right? Shouldn't
this femur be sucked in more? Should the
Q angle be more severe? Should the leg
come in more? Is the ridge of the
glutial tuberosity accurate? In general,
fibers tend to be oriented around a 45°
angle. Some plastic skeletons, you don't
see that because it's all out of whack.
But also, there's no wrapping element.
Muscular tissue has a thickness to it.
And as you move through a range of
motion, you don't always capture that.
For example, if I just represent this
with a straight line and I move up into
hip flexion to stretch the glutes.
Sometimes what you'll see is this cord
doesn't stretch. See that? It just moves
up with it. In real life, you're going
to have a wrapping element like this.
So, you're going to see more stretch.
Yes, it does flatten out a little bit,
but it doesn't come up through the hip
joint center. So, muscles have bulk to
them, and the skeleton can't portray
that wrapping element. So, I'm going to
show you guys a video here of a
freakishly, strong, and muscular woman
performing a deadlift variation here.
And the reason why I'm using this is you
can actually see her glutes. You need a
shredded muscular person to see how the
glutes actually behave. And we can't
capture that with a skeleton. Now,
here's what some research try to do to
provide a solution for that straight
line muscularkeeletal model. We either
try to make multiple points so it's not
a straight line, a series of segments,
or they place a sphere in there so that
the line wraps around it. And these
models are never perfect, which I'll get
to in a minute. Nevertheless, we could
see with the skeleton that it does make
sense that abduction is going to
lengthen the glutes. So, yes, we could
see that going wider in the frontal
plane tends to lengthen the glutes.
We're also involving the sagittal plane
by going into a squat. So when you go
wide and then you end up going deep, do
you end up with a better stretch when
going deep compared to when going
narrower? This is hard to model. We need
mass in there. We need thickness to it.
We'd have to see how it wraps under. And
since it wraps under, you would think
the most stretch on the glutes would be
achieved with a narrower stance compared
to wider stance when sinking really deep
into hip flexion. This is when you might
see narrower stretch the glute max more.
even the lower fibers compared to going
wide. So this is where muscularkeeletal
modeling comes into play. All right
guys, so I'm gonna introduce you to
OpenSim. This is a muscularkeeletal
modeling software created by Scott Delp.
He's a Stanford biomechanics professor
and it's free. So some of you
biomechanics geeks might want to
download this and learn it and toy
around with it. So I'm going to show you
some charts here, okay? I've got charts
for you to check out. The first one is
going to look at the upper glute max
when you go narrow versus wide or
conventional versus sumo. Here is the
stretch on the upper glute max doing a
conventional deadlift or a narrow stance
squat or a single leg leg press with a
narrow stance. Now let's look at the
second chart. What happens when you go
wide? When you go sumo, take a wider
stance. You can see that you get less
stretch on the upper glutes. So if
length was important, sumo would be less
effective for upper glute max
development. Now let's look at the
middle glute max. Here's what you get
going narrow. And now here is what you
get going wider. As you can see with
middle glute max, you get less length
change as well. Sure, in very short
ranges, in extreme ranges of hip
hyperextension that most people don't
even have the mobility to reach here,
you will see a longer glute. But for the
ranges we see during these movements,
which would probably be 0° like neutral
all the way to like maybe, you know, 100
maybe 110 degrees of hip flexion, narrow
has the advantage for greater stretch.
Okay. But what about the lower glutius
maximus? Remember, the lower glutius
maxima has the longest fibers and also
grow the most from hip extension
training. They can increase their muscle
volume by 20% in just a couple months of
progressive resistance training using
either squats or hip thrusts. What
happens to the length of the lower glute
max when you go from narrow to wide?
Well, here's a chart showing narrow
stance and here's a chart showing wider
stance. Now, this range is crazy. It
goes from 30 degrees of hip
hyperextension all the way to 140
degrees of hip flexion for a total of
170 degrees hip range of motion. And
that's a lot. Most people don't have 30°
of hip hyperextension mobility. Most
people don't have 140° of hip flexion
mobility. And even so, you don't reach
those ranges during these movement. Like
I said earlier, I guess with the masses,
it would be maybe like neutral, like 0°
up until like maybe 110°. I'm just
guessing. It could be off by that, but
it's going to be individual specific.
It's going to have a lot to do with your
anthropometry, whether you're doing
squats versus deadlifts, your arm
length. If you have longer femurs,
you'll lean forward more. If you have
longer arms, you'll lean less. But if we
look at this chart, we can see from 30°
of hip hyperextension all the way to
about 80° of hip flexion, sumo actually
stretches the glutes more. And then from
deep hip flexion, from 80° to 140, the
advantage goes to narrow stance. So,
what does this mean? Well, I'm going to
bring up the Plotkin 2023 study again.
As I mentioned earlier, Plotkin 2023
showed that EMG did not predict
hypertrophy. You know what else? It
showed that stretch did not predict
hypertrophy because squats stretch the
glutes more and squats and hipos tied
for glute growth. So, stretch does not
automatically predict hypertrophy. We've
seen that in the case of the glutes.
We've seen it with delts. We've seen it
with some studies on the quads and the
arm muscles. It's going to have a lot to
do with the inherent biomechanics of the
exercise, but it also may have to do
with the muscle in question. So talk to
any muscle hypertrophy specialist and
ask them what is the primary driver of
muscle hypertrophy. What drives muscle
growth? And they will answer mechanical
tension. Tension on the muscle is
thought to be the primary factor.
Anything else is thought to be a far
second or third factor for muscle
growth. for example, metabolic stress,
muscle damage, hormones. These are
thought to play a very minor role or
even a negligible or they could even be
counterproductive in some circumstances.
So what is mechanical tension? Well, in
biomechanics, we call it muscle force.
And I want to show you how open sim
models muscle force with the glutius
maximus. So if you move through a full
range of motion, this is with a narrow
stance, you will see both active and
passive force curves. For active force
comes from activating the motor unit. So
picture maximally activating the glutius
maximus muscle. And that red line shows
you the force that's produced from the
active component. And now you see the
blue line as well. Those forces come
from stretching the glutes through a
full range of motion. So you've heard
that stretches everything. Well, what
gives? Why is it stretch adding way more
tension than this? I don't know.
Muscular skeletal modeling is very
challenging. You have to rely on a lot
of assumptions. So is this realistic?
Unfortunately, we don't have any studies
on the length tension relationship. So,
we don't know the active and passive
force angle curves as you move
throughout the range of motion. But the
way this biomechanical software program
models the glute max is it does not show
the stretch adding a ton of tension. We
also don't know if active and passive
tension provide unique hypertrophy
stimuli. Do you get some signals coming
from being activated and having that
pulling force and different signaling
coming from stretch signaling as the
muscle is stretched or is it just total
tension on the muscle regardless of
whether it comes from active or passive
elements? There is some evidence that
tighten is going to become much stiffer
when it's activated. But if you activate
a muscle through the full range of
motion, is it just total tension or are
there unique stimuli? Unfortunately, we
don't know the answer to this yet. So,
we're just going to look at total
tension. So if I blend the red and blue
lines together, you come up with one
line, the green line here. This is your
total muscle force throughout the range
of motion. And you see on this chart
here that you get peak tension from
around 20 to 40° of hip flexion. And as
you continue to stretch the glutes,
total tension doesn't rise up past that
peak component in the middle range
there. So if this length tension curve
is accurate, this cast doubt on whether
stretch is very important for glute
growth. As long as you reach 40° of hip
flexion, you're good. You don't need to
go deeper than that. But I doubt this is
accurate. Models rely on a ton of
assumptions. Nevertheless, I redrrew
that green line to make it a red line
here to compare it to sumo. So here you
have conventional or narrow stance, this
red line here. And now you go wide and
you have a blue line. And that is the
tension curve or the total muscle force
curve with hip extension in a wide
stance. Now, I used 50 degrees of
abduction. I don't know if that's
accurate. Maybe I went overboard. This
would be going really wide. And again,
this is just for the lower glute max.
We're just looking at lower glute max
here. But looking at muscle force, you
get the same peaks. Yes, you're getting
more tension on the glutes at shorter
ranges using sumo, but then you're
getting more tension at longer ranges
going narrow. If you're at the far right
of the graph, say you were just doing
super deep pulses, you only do lengthen
partials, then judging by this graph,
you'd probably see more tension on the
glutes doing narrow stance compared to
wide stance. On the other hand, if all
you do is shorten pulses, instead of
lengthened partials, you're doing
shortened partials. You're doing hip
thrust lockouts. You're doing 45°ree
hyper lockouts, then this would suggest
that you'd see better results going wide
compared to going narrow. So, should we
be doing hip thrust pulses with a wide
stance for the lower glute max? Maybe we
should. We have muscle length and
mechanical tension evidence using
muscularkeeletal modeling that suggests
that it is beneficial. So, how do these
models work? You have to input a lot of
characteristics. They're very
complicated. I remember really looking
into it with uh coach Chasm and we found
a lot of flaws. He geeked out on it and
we were looking at the effects of, for
example, hypertrophy, like having very
muscular glutes on these length tension
relationships. We found out one model
changed the tendon slack in order to
make it work. But how do you know what
the tendon slack of the glutius maximus
is? I've never seen that measured. So
while I don't think muscularkeeletal
modeling is all that, I hope what you
can deduce from this video is nothing is
all that. Nothing aside from training
studies is all that because we've seen
pitfalls with EMG, with stretch, with
muscularkeeletal modeling, and with
anecdotes. And even with training
studies, you can have flaws because
sometimes the researchers don't employ
top-notch coaches and they don't know
how to coach the lifts properly. So when
you see a training study, you're
assuming that proper form was used,
proper progression is it's not always
the best coaches that are helping to
carry out these training studies. The
other thing about this modeling research
is it's hard to replicate the ranges of
motion. You tend to pick one point and
then model it through a range, but it
doesn't model what's actually happening.
For example, in my model, all I did was
kick the thigh out to 50° of abduction,
but when you come down into a sumo
deadlift in deep hip flexion, you're
internally rotating the femurss a little
bit. And then as you come up, you're
externally rotating the hips. And you
can't include that in on the model. So,
you don't get 3D modeling here. It kind
of represents two dimensions. And it's
not going to replicate the natural 3D
movement that we see in the hip socket
being a ball and socket joint which is
capable of hip flexion and extension,
hip abduction and adduction, and hip
internal and external rotation. Now,
let's talk about some practical
consideration. Check out this picture of
different hip anatomies. Okay, our hips
come in all shapes and sizes. You have
different heads of the femur, different
orientation of the sockets, different
depth of the sockets, different pelvic
shapes. The angles are oriented
uniquely. You may have a particular hip
anatomy that is very well suited for
going narrow but not well suited for
going wide. Or vice versa. You may be
built to go wide but not built to go
narrow at least when going deep. Right?
These unique hip anatomies tend to
appear problematic the deeper you go in
deep hip flexion. That's when you see
more incidences of femoral acid table
impingement syndrome. FAI that happens
when you go deep and you actually
impinge on the structures. And it's not
only our hip anatomy that differs
drastically from one individual to the
next. It's also our glute anatomy. Check
out this picture here of this woman
kneeling. You see that the glute max
actually inserts lower onto the femur
that you would assume. And some people
have much lower glute max insertions
than others. Like here's my friend Daja.
She's known for having lower glute max
insertions compared to other
competitors. And it's nice in bikini to
have this because the glute appears much
fuller. It helps out with different
poses. But I want to direct you guys to
a paper published by Duda. This was
published like 30 years ago. The paper
was titled variability of femoral muscle
attachments. So this first image just
shows you the six specimens they used.
So you can see they're between 67 and 81
years old. So older subjects. You got
four males and two females. You got
totally different femur and tibulan.
Okay. Now this next image I want to show
you shows the different specimens.
Right? So you look at the muscles on the
left. Glutius maxis 1, two, and three.
One is the upper glute max. two is the
middle glute max and three is the lower
glute max. So on the left is the area of
the femoral muscle attachment. So you
can see how it differs from specimens 1
through six. In particular, look at
specimen one having way more lower glute
max area than upper glute max area.
Whereas specimen 3 has way more upper
glute max area compared to lower for the
muscle attachments. And then we slide
over to the right and we look at muscle
volumes. It just has specimen 3, four,
five, and six. But yeah, look at
specimen 3. Look how crazy the the
muscle volume is of the lower glute max.
And look at specimen five, how small the
upper glute max volume is. Now look at
the next image and this shows you moment
arms. This is your leverage. And they
average the leverages together of hip
extension, abduction, external rotation
to get a good picture of what the glute
max is doing for these different
individuals. And this is insane. Look at
specimen number three. This is millime.
So 100 millm. So 10 cm moment arm for
the lower glute max for specimen 3. So
you look at specimen 3 and four, they
have really good leverage of the glutes.
Where you look at specimen 5 and 6, they
do not have good leverage. Specimen 6,
you got 1.8 cm and 2.2 cm leverage for
their glutius maximus. This is insane.
So you're seeing almost a five times
greater leverage with one individual
compared to the next. And remember,
torque equals muscle force times the
momentum. Think of a wrench. the turning
force or the torque I produce with the
wrench is going to be equal to the force
I put into the wrench times the distance
between where I apply the force and the
center of rotation. So moment arm is
half the battle here. So this just goes
to show you how different our glutes
are. And this might influence how well
we activate the glutes because if you
have better leverage, you think your
central nervous system would incorporate
the glutes more if you have great
leverage. But I digress. Let's dive into
our conclusions. I've come up with six
conclusions from the available evidence.
The first is that anecdotes, EMG, hip
loading, stretch, they just provide
clues. They can't be used for really
solid evidence. They're just clues. The
second is that tension is very
promising, but more work needs to be
done with the modeling softwares to make
sure we're providing accurate levels of
tension. In this case, we don't know
whether Open Sim accurately measures
muscle force or not. It has a lot to do
with the resting sarcomir length because
at resting position different muscles
have different beginning starting length
and then they have different levels of
stretch throughout the range of motion
and this greatly influences how much
active versus passive force you receive
throughout the range of motion. But I do
think that muscle force could accurately
predict muscle hypertrophy over time. I
just don't think we're there yet. The
third conclusion is that it's a pretty
safe bet to me to say that if you use
around 80° of hip flexion or less, wider
is probably going to be better for lower
glute max development. If you go much
deeper beyond 80° of hip flexion, then
narrow might be better than sumo. So, in
the modeling showed that 80° of hip
flexion, which is about right here, all
the way to 30° of hip hyperextension,
which is probably more range than people
have, the lower glute max tends to
experience greater stretch and tension
going wider. So, if this is the range
you use most, then go wider for lower
glute max growth. But if you go deeper
from here to here, if you tend to go
really deep with things, then narrower
might be better for the lower glute max.
The fourth conclusion is that you need
to do what's best for your hip anatomy
because what feels best for you is going
to heavily influence the pain that you
experience during exercise over the long
haul as well as potential damage to the
structures and injuries. And this is
important over, you know, a 30 40 year
old lifting career. So, we don't pay
enough attention to this. We don't talk
about enough. When you're in your teens
and your 20s, all you care about is
progressive overload, getting stronger.
But look at pro athletes. when they're
older, they're beat up. A lot of their
knees are shot. There's a sweet spot for
loading on the structures, and you need
to care about what feels best for you.
And don't just push through pain. Work
around it. So, don't just think
short-term hypertrophy over the next
year. Think of long-term hypertrophy
over the next several decades. The fifth
conclusion is if they both feel good, do
both. Do some sumo stuff, do some narrow
stuff. Sometimes it feels good to do
some sumo leg press. I like doing sumo
hip thrust pulses from time to time. I
also like going narrow particularly on
my Romanian deadlifts and not just
stance width but also foot flare.
Sometimes keep the feet straight
sometimes turn them out more es for the
lockout work because one thing is
certain variety is good for adherence
and like I just said in my last point
you need to consider hypertrophy over
several decades. Switching it up
increases longevity as a lifter. It
makes it more exciting. Variety is the
spice of life. And the final and last
conclusion is don't always listen to the
biomechanical bros, particularly the
ones who make bold black and white
claims. Unfortunately, these days anyone
can call themselves a biomechanist.
Anyone can pretend that they're ahead of
the research and they know everything.
But until we have at least one
highquality published training study,
but ideally, you know, three to five,
then we can't be certain about this
topic. And based on all the evidence, it
does make sense to include some sumo
work, some wide stance work for the
lower glute max. Please leave a comment.
I'd love to hear what you think. Do you
love sumo? Do you hate it? Does it feel
good? Do you feel the glutes working
more when you go wide or working less?
If you love the video, make sure you hit
like. And please give me a follow, even
though I'm the most sporadic fitness
content creator on YouTube. My apologies
for that, but one thing is certain. I am
Brent Conturus, aka the glute guy.